<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation giuen by the discreet lords and states, against the slanders laid vpon the euangelicall and reformed religion, by the Arminians and separatists containing all the points, accusations, declarations and confessions, taken out of the last prouinciall synode holden at Arnhem, the 15. day of September last past. 1618. Together with the seuerall examinations and confessions (at Vtrecht and the Hage) of one Leydenberg, pentioner of Leyden, and Taurinus; with their sodaine and fearefull ends.</title>
            <author>Nederlandse Hervormde Kerk. Synoden, (1618 : Gelderland, Netherlands)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122270</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857422</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857422</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23159</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01582)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23159)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1066:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation giuen by the discreet lords and states, against the slanders laid vpon the euangelicall and reformed religion, by the Arminians and separatists containing all the points, accusations, declarations and confessions, taken out of the last prouinciall synode holden at Arnhem, the 15. day of September last past. 1618. Together with the seuerall examinations and confessions (at Vtrecht and the Hage) of one Leydenberg, pentioner of Leyden, and Taurinus; with their sodaine and fearefull ends.</title>
                  <author>Nederlandse Hervormde Kerk. Synoden, (1618 : Gelderland, Netherlands)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 [i.e. 19], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed according to the Dutch originals, at London, by G[eorge] E[ld] for Th[omas]: Th[orpe]: and Richard Chambers, and are to be solde at the signe of the blacke Beare in Paules Church-yard [at the shop of Edward Blount],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dutch original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Eld's, Thorpe's, and Blount's names from STC and addendum.</note>
                  <note>Page numbers 18 and 19 are transposed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nederlandse Hervormde Kerk. --  Synoden, (1618 : --  Gelderland, Netherlands)</term>
               <term>Arminianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Remonstrants --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23159:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23159:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PROCLAMATION GIVEN BY THE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CREET <hi>LORDS</hi> AND <hi>STATES,</hi> againſt the ſlanders laid vpon the Euangelicall and Reformed Religion, by the ARMINIANS and SEPARATISTS: Containing all the Points, Accuſations, Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Confeſſions, taken out of the laſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall Synode holden at <hi>Arnhem,</hi> the 15. day of <hi>September</hi> laſt paſt. 1618.</p>
            <p>Together with the ſeuerall Examinations and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions (at <hi>Vtrecht</hi> and the <hi>Hage</hi>) of one <hi>Leyden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> Pentioner of <hi>Leyden,</hi> and <hi>Taurinus;</hi> with their ſodaine and fearefull ends.</p>
            <p>Printed according to the Dutch Originals, <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> By G. E. for T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: TH: and RICHARD CHAMBERS, and are to be ſolde at the ſigne of the blacke Beare in <hi>Paules Church-yard.</hi> 1618.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:23159:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:23159:2"/>
            <head>The Gouernour, Chancellour, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, in the name of the Lords and Eſtates of the Dukedome of <hi>Gelderlandt,</hi> and County of <hi>Zutphen,</hi> doe giue to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand:</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT whereas, not onely out of theſe Prouinces, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicall Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers thereof (tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row publique Writings and publiſhed Bookes, by the <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi>) but alſo within theſe Prouinces, (as well amongſt the common people, as by written Remonſtrations deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ouer to the diſcreete Lords and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:23159:3"/>
States and their Deputies) is brought in queſtion; about ſundry terrible and blaſphemous Poynts of Doctrine: whereby the Euangelicall Doctrine and the Teachers thereof are defamed and made cauſers of the oppreſſion of the Truth, diſturbation of the Policie of Gouernment, lamentation &amp; griefe of many zealous Soules and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, departing and ſeducing of others, and the augmentation of the enemies of the Truth. The diſcreet Lords and Eſtates, out of ſundry and manifeſt Reaſons heretofore giuen by the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts</hi> in Church-matters, are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to command the ſaid Points deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately to be examined, and in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue Claſſe, whether any of the Teachers might be found guilty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Which done, they of the Claſſe, which were moſt ſuſpected and guilty therein, haue declared, firſt, in their Aſſemblies, and afterwards in preſence
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:23159:3"/>
of the Deputies in the Prouinciall Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node, for themſelues, and in the name of their Committees, that they neuer held or acknowledged, nor yet hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will hold or acknowledge that the ſame Poynts are the opinions of the Reformed Church. Alſo, that they know not, that euer the ſame was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in ſuch ſence and meaning by any of the Teachers in the Reformed Church, but much rather, that they had an horror and trembling to thinke the ſame, deteſting and renouncing the ſame in the higheſt degree. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon alſo, thoſe that were any wayes affected to the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Arminians,</hi> and authors of the foreſaid obiected Poynts, to be the old Reformed opinion; haue acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and confeſſed (in the aforeſaid Prouinciall Synode) that they had pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome of the ſame through ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, ſome out of a wicked preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23159:4"/>
and ſome out of vaine-glory, acquitting and holding their fellow-Brethren free and guiltleſſe therein, being heartily ſory that they euer did lay the ſame to their charge, promiſing hereafter neuer to charge any body with any ſuch like Accuſations eyther publiquely or priuately. But much more to doe their vttermoſt endeuour to moderate the ſame, and to ſet them in peace and quietneſſe, who therewith were any wayes troubled or moleſted, and to helpe to defend and take away all further ſlanders and accuſations one of another.</p>
            <p>Wee therefore conſidering that the aforeſaid ſlanders and calumnies of the Doctrine and Teachers of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicall Reformed Churches, (as well at home as abroad) is rumored both farre and neare, and deſiring to exalt and extoll the ſame, to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of the Truth haue found it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:23159:4"/>
fit and conuenient to extract and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the aforeſaid Poynts and Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Declarations and Confeſſions, out of the Acts of the laſt Prouinciall Synode: So that euery one hauing knowledge therof, may hereafter hold themſelues quiet in Conſcience, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine and continue in the truth of the Euangelicall Reformed Religion, giue no credit to the ſlanders and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections of their enemies, and that thereby the Churches and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty being eſtabliſhed in the accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnitie, Gods glory may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and the Subiects may liue in peace, tranquilitie, and proſperitie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their lawfull Magiſtrates.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen in the Councell of</hi> Gelderlandt <hi>at</hi> Arnhem, <date>
                     <hi>the 15. of September,</hi> 1618.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Subſigned <hi>E. Engelen.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="extract">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:23159:5"/>
            <head>An Extract of the Acts of the Synode of <hi>Gelderlandt,</hi> held at <hi>Arnhem</hi> in Iuly, 1618.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Acts of the <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors</hi> of the <hi>Synode</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing related, the firſt ſeparation or diuiſion of theſe Countries was alſo declared, and the writings and Controverſies which followed there vpon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and how the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters about the Towne and Countrie of <hi>Nymegam,</hi> in their firſt Letters and Writings (ſent and deliuered vnto the Countrey) had obiected tenne Poynts or Poſitions, like as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God from all eternitie hath reprobated the moſt part of mankinde,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23159:5"/>
and ineuitably ordayned them to dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, without any reſpect of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe and ſinnes, which they might or ſhould commit, or of the ſinne of <hi>Adam:</hi> onely according to his delight and pleaſure, the which hee taketh in the reuealing of the glory of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and might.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or if that God in the aforeſaid Reprobation in any wiſe hath regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> or the originall ſinne thereout proceeding, but not any actuall ſinne or vnbeliefe, whereby the Reprobates could deſerue this Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation more then others.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That amongſt theſe Reprobates are an infinite number of young Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the faithfull, which dying in their Infancie without any actuall ſin, poore innocent Sucklings are taken away and caſt into the fire of Hell; ſo that it auaileth them not to haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the holy Baptiſme, nor that any
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23159:6"/>
man ſhould pray vnto God Almighty for them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That God from all eternitie hath elected, and inreſiſtably or dayned to ſaluation the leſſer part of mankinde, without reſpect of their beliefe, as a condition neceſſary to ſaluation; yea, alſo without any motion of Chriſt, as the meriting cauſe of ſaluation, onely by meere chance and good lucke in ſome men, without any reſpect of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities: ſo that Chriſt is onely the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the ſaid Decree: and Beliefe a fruit of the Election.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That God towards the fulfilling of his eternall immutable Decree, hath created the moſt part of mankinde for damnation, and with this intention made them that they ſhould be damned.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That God forceth and prouoketh men to ſinne, yea, and that hee is the cauſe of ſinne.</p>
            <p n="7">7 That God hath giuen his Sonne
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:23159:6"/>
to be an Aduocate for the relapſed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane generation, whoſe ſacrifice would be sufficient to ſatisfie for all mens ſinnes, yet that his intention was not that Chriſt ſhould dye for all, but onely for a few: and that the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, whenſoeuer the Goſpell is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto them, muſt alſo beleeue that Chriſt dyed for them; and if they did not beleeue ſo, were therefore iuſtly damned.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That God ſendeth his holy Word vnto many Reprobates, and inuites them to his communion, not that they ſhould thereby bee conuerted and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt, but expreſly with ſuch an intention that their hearts ſhould be hardned, and therfore more grieuouſly puniſhed: And that thoſe Reprobates muſt acknowledge the aforeſaid voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; inuitation of the Lord (through his holy Word) a worke of Grace and Mercy, for the which they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:23159:7"/>
to thanke the LORD.</p>
            <p n="9">9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That the Elect are conuerted, and Faith and Beliefe infuſed into them with an inreſiſtable ſtrength, in ſuch ſort that they cannot chuſe but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and beleeue in Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> like as (on the contrary) it is impoſſible for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates to attaine true Faith, what meanes ſoeuer they vſe, although they did doe all the workes of the Saints.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That hee that once beleeueth in Chriſt, cannot wholly nor finally looſe the ſame, nor fall from Grace through careleſneſſe, nor through the greateſt and higheſt deadly ſinne, as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultry, Murther and the like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that hee being fallen into moſt heynous ſinnes, muſt of neceſſitie bee conuerted afore his death, by vertue of the aforeſaid abſolute and in euitable Decree.</p>
            <p>Maintayning that ſome Teachers in theſe Prouinces doe teach and hold the ſame, and do vndertake to thruſt them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:23159:7"/>
in for the opinions of the Reformed Churches. In conſideration whereof the foure Claſſes, <hi>Teil, Zuophen, Ouer,</hi> and <hi>Neder veluwen,</hi> haue ſolicited, that conſidering they haue declared, and do by theſe preſents declare, neuer to haue acknowledged the ſame, nor now to acknowledge the ſame to be the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſentences of the Reformed Churches: nor to know that the ſaid Poynts were euer maintained by any of the Teachers of the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in that ſence and meaning: but that they were much more abaſhed and aſtonied thereat, deteſting and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the ſame in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: That thoſe perſons might be ſpecified by their particuler names which euer intended or maintained the ſame, and did their vttermoſt to make them paſſe for Poynts of Beliefe in theſe Prouinces, whereof they in their firſt and ſecond writings haue ſo often
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23159:8"/>
made mention, leauing them that are not of vs to anſwer for themſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In the name of them of South-<hi>Holland,</hi> Doctor <hi>Henricus Arnoldi</hi> hath declared, in preſence of the aforeſaid Claſſes, to deteſt and renounce the ſame, and if ſo bee they could charge any body therwith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they would make means that hee ſhould appeare in this preſent place, to the end hee might cleare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe before this Aſſembly, or if he were found guilty, acknowledge his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ault<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo the Commiſſaries of both the Countries, in the name thereof, and of the Honourable Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> haue earneſtly beſought and solicited, that the ſame might bee publiſhed in theſe Prouinces to the end the Lords and Magiſtrates might proceed according to Iuſtice and equitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd theſe Prouinces from ſuch blaſphemies.</p>
            <p>That o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſentences and opinions are that God Almighty will eternally tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23159:8"/>
in the pit of Hell, innumerable young Children: Notwithſtanding that they were of beleeuing parents, and that onely becauſe of originall ſin, ſo that the aforeſaid Children haue no more hope of ſaluation then the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Angels.</p>
            <p>That wee doe holde the opinion of Churches, and not Gods Word the rule of our Beleefe: and that we are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in much like to the Papiſts, as if the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church could not erre.</p>
            <p>That the Confeſſion and Catechiſme is <hi>Norma ſecundaria Fidei,</hi> a ſecondary rule of Faith, as if we ſaid that the holy Scripture becomes to be a rule of our Beleiefe, when ſhee is expounded ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſence and meaning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Confeſſion and Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme.</p>
            <p>Vnto theſe and ſuch like accuſations, as alſo to the tenne foreſaid Poynts or Poſitions, the Brethren of <hi>Nymegam</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:23159:9"/>
and <hi>Bommel,</hi> for themſelues, and in the name of their fellow-Brethren of the <hi>Arminian</hi> opinion in the ſame quarter; haue for their anſwer declared: That they had ſatisfied themſelues, and with alacritie liſtned to the Declarations of the Brethren of the foure Claſſes, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to that which Doctor <hi>Henricus Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noldi</hi> had annexed thereunto out of the name of the contra-Remonſtrants or old Reformed in <hi>Holland.</hi> And doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that they did place ſome of the ſaid Accuſations through euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, ſome out of a naughty preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſome out of vaine-glory, and doe acquit and diſcharge all and euery of the aſſembled Brethren, and are heartily ſory that euer they accuſed them therewith, and deſired that they would not bee ſo highly offended, but to pardon them, and to bury it in the fire of loue, and place it in obliuion, and promiſed hereafter not to charge any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23159:9"/>
man with ſuch accuſations, either pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely or priuately: but rather to doe their vttermoſt endeuour to moderate the ſame, and to ſet them in peace and quietneſſe that therwith are any waies moleſted, and helpe to take away all occaſion of diſcord and diſſention one with another.</p>
            <p>Alſo, that if ſo bee in time to come they were found to haue committed any thing here-againſt, they doe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſubmit themſelues vnto all cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Nationall or particular Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes, and alſo vpon paine of baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>All this being witneſſed with words, the Aſſembly was confirmed with ſhaking of hands with the Preſident.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="confession">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:23159:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Ledenberch</hi> his Confeſsion both at <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trecht</hi> and the <hi>Hage:</hi> Alſo, the death of <hi>Taurinus,</hi> and how the ſaid <hi>Leden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berch</hi> murthered himſelfe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, to breake the Vnion and to ordaine another forme or kinde of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the helpe and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Prouinces of <hi>Holland, V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trecht,</hi> and <hi>Oueryſſell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to depoſe his Princely Excellencie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to make the Religion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, to maintaine and aſſiſt one another therein with life &amp; goods.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, that they haue communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame with ſome of the Councell
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23159:10"/>
of <hi>France,</hi> and therunto deſired aduice and counſell.</p>
            <p>Further, ſome ſeuen or eight Months ſince, that <hi>Taurinus</hi> had made a Booke called the <hi>Waech-Schael</hi> or Ballance, and that the ſame was corrected and amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Vtenbogaert,</hi> and that the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall was deliuered into the hands of ſome of the States of <hi>Vtrecht.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="confession">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:23159:11"/>
            <head>Their Confeſsions in the <hi>Hage.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrſt, that they would renounce and breake the generality and vnitie of the State.</p>
            <p>Secondly, change and alter the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to degrade the Prince of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, to maſſacre the people of the Townes which were their greateſt enemies, or offered reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, if that fayled, to take in aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ſome forraigne Potentates, as <hi>Spaine</hi> or <hi>Brabant,</hi> deliuering vnto them <hi>Vtrecht, Nimwegen, Berghen op Zoom,</hi> and the <hi>Briel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 23. of <hi>September</hi> (being Sunday) <hi>Taurinus</hi> dyed at <hi>Bockhouen,</hi> a mile from <hi>Heuſden,</hi> and was buried the Friday af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at <hi>Scheidam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 27. of the foreſaid Moneth, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denberch</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:23159:11"/>
was examined, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the aboueſaid, and thereafter ſaid to his Son, I haue confeſſed that which will coſt life and goods, and hauing two daies afore conueyed a table-knife into ſome ſecret place, commanded to lay his breeches by his Bed: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, hee ſaid to his Son, If chance thou heareſt any noiſe to night, be ſtill, for I haue not beene at ſtoole theſe two dayes: and then betweene one and two of the clocke in the night hee roſe, and taking a pen-knife out of his penner, hee thruſt it into his belly to the haft not farre from his Nauell, and feeling that he was not ſped, he tooke the table<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knife, and therewith cut his throate, and ſtabd himſelfe with the ſame knife into his ſhort ribs, and laſtly into the breſt: his ſonne awaking, it was alas too late for his poore ſoule.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
